Guide to the Saint-Mémin Print Collection 1794-1808 PR 226
New-York Historical Society
Saint-Mémin Print Collection
1794-1808
New-York Historical Society
PR 226
4 Linear feet (3 boxes, 1 drawer)
Collection of engravings by the French engraver Charles Balthazar Julien Fevret de Saint-Saint-Mémin. Most are profile portrait engravings, but several early views of New York City are also included.
Provenance
The collection is comprised of gifts from various donors. The album of portrait engravings was a gift from the Estate of Hall Park McCullough in 1973.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Biographical Note
Charles Balthazar Julien Fevret de Saint-Mémin was born in France in 1770. He served as an officer in the French Army, and was exiled after the French Revolution. When he arrived in the United States in 1793, he began to teach himself the arts of engraving and painting, producing some views of New York City as early as 1794. His first work was published in 1796, the year he began a portrait business with Thomas Bluget de Valdenuit, a fellow Frenchman. The two utilized the physiognotrace, a device whereby a sitter's profile was traced by a bar, and a pantograph, with a piece of chalk attached to its end, drew the same profile in a smaller dimension onto a piece of paper. Details were then added to the outline drawing. Another pantograph was used to trace the drawing and produce a continuous line engraving on a copper plate. Saint-Mémin then utilized a roulette, a tool of his own invention, to produce shading on the engravings. The sitter usually received the drawing, the copper plate and a dozen engravings for a set fee.
While in business with Valdenuit, Saint-Mémin produced the engravings from his partner's drawings. The partnership dissolved after about a year, and Saint-Mémin went on to create both the portrait drawings and engravings himself. He left New York in 1798, and traveled down the east coast of the United States, with stays in Philadelphia, Baltimore, Washington, Richmond, and Charleston. In 1810, Saint-Mémin returned to France, effectively ending his portrait business. He returned briefly to America, but moved to France in 1814, where he lived until his death in 1852. During his stay in America, Saint-Mémin drew a total of more than 900 portraits and engraved more than 800 of these.
Sources:
Miles, Ellen G. Saint-Mémin and the Neoclassical Profile Portrait in the America. Washington: National Portrait Gallery and the Smithsonian Institue Press, 1994.
Morgan, John Hill. "The Work of M. Fevret de Saint-Mémin," in the Brooklyn Museum Quarterly, January 1918, Vol. V, No. 1.
Scope and Content Note
The Saint-Mémin Print Collection spans the period from 1794-1808 and contains engravings made by Charles Balthazar Julien Fevret de Saint-Mémin. The collection is divided into two series: Portraits; and Views.
Arrangement
The collection is divided into two series:
Missing Title
Series I. Portraits
Series II. Views
Related Material at the New-York Historical Society
Original printing plates by Saint-Mémin, including several for prints in this collection, can be found in the Printing Plate File (PR 057). Modern restrikes of Saint-Mémin's plates can be found throughout the Portrait File (PR 052). The Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Drawings also holds a copy of The St-Memin Collection of Portraits, with photographs of 760 etchings by Gurney & Son (New York: E. Dexter, 1862). At least one map by Saint-Mémin is in the N-YHS Library's Map Collection. Drawings by Saint-Mémin can be found in the N-YHS Museum.
New York (N.Y.) -- Pictorial works.; Engravings (prints); Portraits.; Legislators -- United States -- Portraits.; Valdenuit, Thomas Bluget de, 1763-1846
- Series I: Portraits
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I. Portraits date from 1796 to 1808 and contains profile portrait engravings, made after drawings by Saint-Mémin and his early partner Valdenuit, assisted by a physiognotrace mechanism. Profile portraits in this collection were made in New York, Philadelphia, Washington, Richmond, Baltimore, and Burlington, NJ, often of government notables and upper-class urban dwellers. The series is arranged into three subseries: Portrait album; Framed portraits, and Loose portraits.
  In 1862, Elias Dexter published a book of Saint-Mémin's American portraits, each of which was photographed by Gurney & Son. While some sitters were misidentified in Dexter's volume, it has been used as a standard means for identification of the Saint-Mémin portraits. Dexter's number (which does not correspond to a chronological or alphabetical listing) follows the sitter's name in the Container List.
  - Subseries I. Portrait Album
    The Portrait album holds twenty-eight portraits, bound together in a small, leather-covered album. In general, these engravings were trimmed to their plate borders and pasted on to the album pages. There does not seem to be an order to the portraits; they have been listed in the container list in the order they appear in the album.
    The portraits in the album are listed as they appear. Inscriptions are noted.
    - Saint-Mémin, Charles Balthazar Julien Fevret de (D. 5), 1804 (Offsite-box 1)
      General note
      Philadelphia
    - Somerville, William Clarke (D. 624), 1808 (Offsite-box 1)
      Richmond
    - Bayard, James Asheton (D. 421), 1801 (Offsite-box 1)
      Inscr. "Drawn & engrd. by St. Memin Philadela."
    - Griffin, Thomas (D. 479), 1805 (Offsite-box 1)
      Washington
    - Clarke, William (D. 477), 1807 (Offsite-box 1)
    - Gilmor, Mary Ann Smith (D.284), 1803 (Offsite-box 1)
      Inscr. "St. M. delt. & sct." Baltimore
    - Dana, Samuel Whittelsey (D. 430), 1806 (Offsite-box 1)
    - Dallas, Alexander James (D. 138), 1801 (Offsite-box 1)
    - Campbell, Levin Hicks (D. 376), 1804 (Offsite-box 1)
      Baltimore
    - Ormsby, Sarah Mahon (D. 38), [1801] (Offsite-box 1)
    - Darieu (D. 256), 1800 (Offsite-box 1)
      Inscr. "Drawn & engrd. by St. Memin Philada."
    - Henry, Isaac (D. 421), 1802 (Offsite-box 1)
    - Thieubert (D. 249), 1803 (Offsite-box 1)
    - Bryan, Joseph (D. 486), 1805 (Offsite-box 1)
    - Coale, Edward Johnson (D. 338), 1804 (Offsite-box 1)
    - Gilmor, William (D. 353), 1803 (Offsite-box 1)
    - Bartlett, Bailey (D. 472), 1800 (Offsite-box 1)
    - Purviance, Samuel Dinsmore (D.431), 1805 (Offsite-box 1)
    - Tucker, Thomas Tudor (D. 412), 1805 (Offsite-box 1)
    - Lewden, Joseph (D. 294), 1802 (Offsite-box 1)
    - Guenet (D. 324), 1803 (Offsite-box 1)
    - Newton, Thomas Jr. (D.497), 1806 (Offsite-box 1)
    - Huger, Benjamin (D. 488), 1805 (Offsite-box 1)
    - Burrall, Jonathan (D. 41), 1798-1803 (Offsite-box 1)
    - Powell, Leven (D. 462), 1800 (Offsite-box 1)
      Inscr. "Drawn & engrd. by St. Memin Philadelphia"
    - Morton, Cornelia Schuyler (D. 37), 1797 (Offsite-box 1)
      Inscr. "St. Memin & Valdenuit No. 27 Pine St. N. York"
    - Boyd, John Parker (D. 222), 1802 (Offsite-box 1)
    - Rush, Benjamin (D. 153), 1802 (Offsite-box 1)
      Inscr. "Benjamin Rush" Philadelphia
  - Subseries II. Framed Portraits
    Framed portraits include three small individual engravings and two larger frames holding composite portraits. The frames may or may not have been contemporary with the engravings, but all seem to be nineteenth century in origin. The largest frame, with a total of twenty engravings, includes eighteen Saint-Mémin portraits of United States Congressmen, as well as two profiles, not by Saint-Mémin, of George Washington and John Adams. Another frame holds four portraits, all New Yorkers.
    - Lincklaen, Helen Ledyard (D. 735), 1798 (Offsite-box 1)
    - Lincklaen, John (D. 111), 1796-1797 (Offsite-box 1)
      New York
    - Thurman, John [Dr. Hill] (D. 56), 1797-1798 (Offsite-box 1)
      Inscr. "St. Memin No. 27 Pine St. N.York"
    - Van Rensselaer, Stephen (D. 55), 1797 (Offsite-box 1)
    - Composite of Four Portraits
      - Barclay, Andrew B.? (D. 60), 1796 (Offsite-box 1)
      - Cuyler, James (D. 78), 1796-1797 (Offsite-box 1)
        Inscr. "Valdenuit & St. Memin No. 27 Pine St. N.York"
      - De Peyster, Nicholas Jr. (D. 86), 1797 (Offsite-box 1)
      - Thompson, Thomas (D. 91), 1797 (Offsite-box 1)
    - Composite of Twenty Portraits (Eighteen by Saint-Mémin). All members of Congress, taken in Washington
      - Baldwin, Simeon (D.448), 1807 (Offsite-box 2)
      - Betton, Silas (D. 500), 1805 (Offsite-box 2)
      - Campbell, John (D. 427), 1806 (Offsite-box 2)
      - Dana, Samuel Whittelsey (D. 430), 1806 (Offsite-box 2)
      - Davenport, John (D. 426), 1806 (Offsite-box 2)
      - Dwight, Thomas (D. 436), 1806 (Offsite-box 2)
      - Griffin, Thomas (D. 479), 1805 (Offsite-box 2)
      - Hastings, Seth (D. 435), 1806 (Offsite-box 2)
      - Hunt, Samuel Jr. [Thompson] (D. 498), [1805] (Offsite-box 2)
      - Lewis, Joseph (D. 474), 1805 (Offsite-box 2)
      - Livingston, Henry Walter (D. 433), 1804 (Offsite-box 2)
      - Lowndes, Thomas (D. 496), 1805 (Offsite-box 2)
      - Nicholson, Joseph Hopper [Stephenson, James] (D 475), [1806] (Offsite-box 2)
      - Pickering, Timothy (D. 434), 1806 (Offsite-box 2)
      - Plumer, William (D. 481), 1806 (Offsite-box 2)
      - Purviance, Samuel Dinsmore (D.431), 1805 (Offsite-box 2)
      - Stedman, William (D. 437), 1805 (Offsite-box 2)
      - Van Rensselaer, Kiliaen Kiliaen (D. 438), 1805 (Offsite-box 2)
  - Subseries III. Loose Portraits
    Seventeen loose portraits are filed alphabetically.
    - Armstrong, William (D. 8), 1797 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1)
      Inscr. "Valdenuit & St. Memin No. 27 Pine St. N.York 97"
    - Bloomfield, Joseph (D. 186), 1798 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 2)
    - Bruce, Archibald (D. 51 ), 1796-1797 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 2)
      Inscr: "St. Memin & Valdenuit No. 27 Pine St. N.York"
    - Bullus, John (D. 511), 1807 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 2)
    - Clinton, Cornelia Tappen (no Dexter #), 1797 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 3)
      Inscr. "St. Memin No. 27 Pine St. N.York"; Four copies
    - Clinton, George (no Dexter #), 1797 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 4)
    - Clinton, James (D. 57), 1797 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 5)
    - Clinton, Mary Little Gray (D. 742), 1798 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 5)
      Inscr: "St. Memin No. 27 Pine St. N.York"
    - Izard, Ralph II (D. 395), 1805 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 6)
    - Lawrence, James (D. 35), 1810 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 7)
      possibly Burlington, N.J.
    - Livingston, Eliza Barclay (D. 302), 1797 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 7)
    - McIlvaine, Joseph (D. 22), 1798 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 8)
      Inscr. "Drawn & engrd by St. Memin Burlington"
    - Robertson, Thomas Bolling (D. 614), 1807-1808 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 9)
    - Simmons, James (D. 216), 1806 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 10)
    - Tayloe, John, III (D. 408), 1806 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 11)
    - Washington, William Augustine III (D. 924), 1804 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 12)
    - White, John Moore (D. 168), 1798-1803 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 12)
      Inscr. "Drawn & engrd by St. Memin Philada."
- Series II: Views
  Series II. Views contains two views of New York City made in 1794-1796, while Saint-Mémin was developing his engraving skills. Shortly after arriving in New York with his father, Saint-Mémin was offered a place to stay by John R. Livingston. Both views are from the Brooklyn shoreline, one from Livingston's home at Mount Pitt (near the present day intersection of Henry and Montgomery Streets.)
  These prints are housed in a flat file drawer.
  - "View of the City and Harbour of New York taken from Mount Pitt, the Seat of John R. Livingston Esqre," etching after his own design, published 1794-1796. (Box Flat File, Folder 13)
  - "View of the City of New York taken from Long Island," etching after his own design, published 1796. Two copies, one colored. (Box Flat File, Folder 13)